<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Quaestiones in libros De anima</title>
        <author>Johannes Dinsdale</author>
        <editor>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="2017.04">
          <title><!-- title [{ms-identifier} Transcription] --></title>
          <date when="2017-04-12">April 12, 2017</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <ref target="http://representationandreality.gu.se">
            Representation and Reality: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives
            on the Aristotelian Tradition
          </ref>
        </authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2017-04-12">April 12, 2017</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="O" n="oriel33">Oxford, Oriel College Library 33, ff. 164r-182v</witness>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="bal">Oxford, Balliol College 311, ff. 148r--181v</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef
          n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
          url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/diplomatic.rng">
      </schemaRef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition</p>
        <p>The transcription has been normalized to classical orthography.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2017-04-12" status="draft" n="2017.04">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" type="translation">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#O" n="164-r"/><cb ed="#O" n="a"/>
        <pb ed="#B" n="148-r"/><cb ed="#B" n="b"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="translation-da-49-l1prooemium">
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-l1prooemium-gq0450">
          <cit>
            <quote type="lemma">Of good and honourable things et cetera</quote>
            <bibl>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
              ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title> I.1 402a1.
            </bibl>
          </cit>
          . In the second book of <title ref="Arist.Ph">Physics</title>, as he intends to
          investigate and present the boundaries and limits of the study of
          physics or the natural philosopher, the
          <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says
          <cit>
            <quote>
              to which extent the natural philosopher ought to investigate the
              species and essence
            </quote>
            <bibl><name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
            ref="#Arist.Ph">Ph.</title> II.2 194b10--11.</bibl>
          </cit>
          , <abbr>viz.</abbr> what the limits are of the study of physics or the
          natural philosopher, which is concerned with species,
          <abbr>viz.</abbr> forms, which are the essences, <abbr>viz.</abbr>
          which are relevant to the definition of the essence. He answers
          <cit>
            <ref>
              in the same passage
            </ref>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              that in whichever way the doctor investigates nerves and the
              metallurgist bronze, so does the natural philosopher investigate
              the form or species and essence,
            </quote>
            <bibl><name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title>Ph.</title> II.2 194b11--12.</bibl>
          </cit>
          as not any consideration of nerves
          pertains to the doctor, nor does whatever thing which can be known
          about bronze pertain to the metallurgist, and similarly is not every
          consideration of forms pertinent to the natural philosopher. We must
          therefore consider how these artificers investigate the
          mentioned subjects.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-1zdal1">
          Let us consider what the different subject matters of the doctor, the
          metallurgist and the natural philosopher are. A doctor primarily seeks
          to produce good health, so when he investigates nerves, it aims at the
          production of good health, therefore whichever consideration of
          nerves, insofar as it strives for good health, pertains to the doctor,
          but if there is some other consideration that goes beyond this, it
          supersedes the doctor's investigation. Similarly, as the metallurgist
          focuses on the matter of artificial instruments, whichever
          investigation of bronze, insofar as it is the matter of artificial
          instruments, pertains to the metallurgist, but if there is some
          consideration that goes beyond this, it evades his consideration. From
          this it is apparent what the object of the natural philosopher's
          knowledge is and to which limit it extends. For whatever is considered
          by a natural philosopher is characterized by movement and change,
          <cit>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              for the things which move but are not moved do not fall within the
              natural philosopher's subject matter
            </quote>
            <ref>
              according to the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> in the
              second book of <title ref="#Arist.Ph">Physics</title>
            </ref>
            <bibl>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
              ref="#Arist.Ph">Ph.</title> II.7 198a26--30.
            </bibl>
          </cit>
          . Hence entirely immaterial forms which are not bound to the motion of
          matter and change of subjects, evade the subject matter of the
          physicist or natural philosopher. But forms which in one way are
          immaterial and in another way are the actuality of matter do fall
          within the subject matter of the natural philosopher or physicist, and
          that is the limit to which the physical consideration extends. But the
          human soul is that sort of form, and hence it is the limit and end of
          physical investigation.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-jon4qo">
          And from this we can establish that there are three types of forms.
          For some are entirely immaterial, both with respect to their
          disposition and substance, and the intelligences, which exist without
          any sensible or intelligible matter
          <cit>
            <ref>
              according to the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> in book
              eight of <title ref="#Arist.Metaph">Metaphysics</title>,
            </ref>
            <bibl>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
              ref="#Arist.Metaph">Metaph.</title> VIII.5 1044b27--29(?)
            </bibl>
          </cit>
          are of this sort; and some
          are entirely material, both with respect to their substance and
          disposition, since their substances and dispositions are realized from
          matter, and the forms of the lower beings are of this sort; but some are
          forms of a medial character which are immaterial with respect to their
          substance and material with respect to their disposition, and the
          human souls are of this sort. Hence the first forms are beyond the subject
          matter of the natural philosopher, but the physical investigation
          begins with the second forms and terminate with the third, for the
          subject matter of the natural philosopher begins with the inferior
          forms and stops with the human soul.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-arr3uu">
          From this it is further apparent which rank this book holds among the
          books on natural philosophy, as the physical and the metaphysical mode
          of investigation in some way are opposed each other. For the natural
          philosopher's mode of investigation has a stopping point in the
          elevated but not in the low, for it has a stopping point with
          reference to the level of abstraction, which is an elevated area,
          since some are so abstract that they exceed the physical subject
          matter, and some are so abstract that the physical subject matter does
          not extend beyond them. But with reference to the level of
          materiality, which is a low level, the natural philosopher does not
          have a stopping point, for there is not another form so concrete with
          reference to matter that it evades the natural philosopher's subject
          matter. Thus the more concrete a form is with reference to matter, the
          more it falls within his subject matter, and this must be understood
          with view to the abstraction from singular items, for if we look to
          things individual and of numerical singularity, that exceeds the
          natural philosopher's subject matter. But the contrary holds for
          metaphysician's mode of investigation, since it has a stopping point
          in the low but not in the elevated, because some form is so concrete
          with respect to matter that the consideration of it does not pertain
          to the metaphysician, but there is no form so abstract that it exceeds
          the metaphysician's consideration, for metaphysics is concerned with
          the highest causes. Hence the more an investigation is concerned with
          abstract things, the more metaphysical it is. This must be understood
          with reference to subject matters based on human inquisition, for if
          there is some abstract subject matter which is acquired through
          inspiration, it exceeds the metaphysician's subject matter, but our
          present reflections are not of that sort.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-gurt68">
          Hence let us understand what has been said in the following way, that
          when there are three essential parts of philosophy (namely natural
          philosophy, mathematics, and divine science) among the arts or
          sciences invented through human inquisition, the metaphysician does
          not recognize any other higher science, but in terms of the level of
          abstraction natural philosophy does not recognize any other lower
          practitioner within the essential parts of philosophy, although there is a
          higher one, but the mathematician recognizes both a higher practice,
          since there is a more abstract one, and a lower, since there is one
          more concrete. Hence, as it has been said, the natural philosopher's
          subject matter takes its beginning with the lower forms and ends
          with the human soul, and from this it is apparent that <title
          ref="#Arist.DA">On the soul</title> holds the sixth place within the
          books on natural philosophy, for <title
          ref="#Arist.Ph">Physics</title> holds the first place, <title
          ref="#Arist.Cael">On the heavens and earth</title> the second, <title
          ref="#Arist.GC">On generation and corruption</title> the third, <title
          ref="#Arist.Met">Meteorology</title> the fourth, <title
          ref="#Ps-Arist.Min">On minerals</title> the fifth, and <title
          ref="#Arist.DA">On the soul</title> the sixth. It is therefore the
          first in order of dignity, although it is the final or sixth in the
          doctrinal order, and hence the
          <cit>
            <ref>
              <name
                  ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says, with a view to its dignity,
            </ref>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              that the description of the soul should be ranked among the first
              sciences.
            </quote>
            <bibl><name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
            ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title> I.1 402a1--7.</bibl>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
