<?xml-model href="../../tools/schema/lombardpress-schema.rnc" type="application/relax-ng-compact-syntax"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Quaestiones in libros De anima</title>
        <author>Johannes Dinsdale</author>
        <respStmt>
          <persName>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</persName>
          <resp>Encoding and transcription</resp>
        </respStmt>
        <editor role="translator">Michael Stenskjær Christensen</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1.0-dev">
          <date when="2016-11-13">November 13, 2016</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</publisher>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref
          target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative
          Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="bal">
            Oxford, Balliol College 311, ff. 148r--181v
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0"
                 target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/1.0/critical.rng">
      </schemaRef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the
          LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a critical edition
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2016-11-13" status="draft" n="0.1.0">
          <p>First draft of finished edition.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="la">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="startsOn">
        <pb n="148-v" ed="#B"/><cb n="a"/>
        <pb n="164-r" ed="#O"/><cb n="b"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="da-49-l1q1">
        <head>
          <supplied ana="#meta-text">
            Question 1: Whether a science about the soul can be acquired by us
          </supplied>
        </head>
        <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-274hkz">
          So it is asked first whether a science about the soul can be acquired
          by us.
        </p>
        <div ana="#rationes-principales-contra">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-j01jdw">
            It seems that it cannot.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-ysmgk1" ana="#rationes-principales-contra" n="1">
            That about which there is a science is intelligible, <seg
            ana="#quia">since</seg> when a science is a <seg
            ana="#habitus">state</seg> of the intellect, the object of the
            science ought to be intelligle; but the soul is not intelligible,
            <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> all our knowledge comes from the
            senses, and <seg ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg> itself does
            not take place without phantasms, but the soul is not available to
            sense perception, nor does it create phantasms; ergo et cetera.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-mjzkyp" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="2">
            Further, one and the same thing cannot be moving and moved at the
            same time, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> then the same thing would be
            in act and potentcy in the same respect; but that which is known is
            moving with respect to that which knows; ergo one and the same thing
            cannot be knowing and known, but that would be the case if there
            were a science about the soul.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-mjgjs9" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="3">
            Further,
            <cit>
              <quote type="paraphrase">
                <phr type="#analogy">
                  just as the eye of the night-raven <seg
                  ana="#se-habet">stands</seg> to the light of the sun, so does
                  our intellect <seg ana="#se-habet">stand</seg> to those things
                  which are most <seg ana="#manifestissima">clear</seg> in nature,
                </phr>
              </quote>
              <bibl>
                Cf. Arist. <title ref="#Arist.Metaph"> Metaph.</title> II.1
                993b9--11 (νυκτερίς).
              </bibl>
            </cit>
            to which the soul belongs, at least the human soul; but the eye of
            the night-raven cannot apprehend the light of the sun; ergo et
            cetera.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-xdpfxs" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="4">
            Further, our <seg ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg> is
            continuous and temporal; but the soul, since it is indivisible and
            perpetual, is neither continuous nor temporal; ergo et cetera.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#rationes-principales-pro">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-o9whrl">
            The opposite <seg ana="#patet">holds</seg> according to the
            determination of the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name>.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#determinatio">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-ywem12" ana="#determinatio" n="1">
            <seg ana="#dicendum">It must be said</seg> that <seg
            ana="#cum+subj">since</seg> science is a <seg
            ana="#habitus">state</seg> acquired by demonstration, and three
            elements are required for a demonstration (that is, a subject, an
            <seg ana="#passio">attribute</seg>, and a principle by which the
            <seg ana="#passio">attribute</seg> is ascribed to the subject),
            where these three can be found it can be said that there is a
            science. <seg ana="#autem">But</seg> now the soul is some sort of
            subject which has <seg ana="#proprietas">properties</seg> and <seg
            ana="#passio">attributes</seg>, as will be apparent below. But there
            are some principles by whic these <seg
            ana="#passio">attributes</seg> can be <seg
            ana="#probare">proved</seg> concerning the soul. For if <seg
            ana="#quod-quid">the definition</seg> of the soul is accepted as the
            middle term,
            <app>
              <lem>
                by that the <seg ana="#propria-passio">property</seg> of the
                soul can be concluded to belong to the soul
              </lem>
              <note>
                The latin reads <quote>per ipsum concludi potest propria passio
                eius de anima</quote>. It is ambiguous to me what the
                <mentioned>eius</mentioned> qualifies, but it is here
                interpreted to qualify <mentioned>passio</mentioned> and refer
                to the soul.
              </note>
            </app>
            , and in this way something can be known about the soul or there can
            be some sort of science about the soul.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-t57fj3" ana="#determinatio" n="2">
            Further, accidents are not things by themselves but belong to
            something else. Ergo one who knows the accidents can be led to a
            <seg ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg> about that which they belong
            to. But now many accidents that belong to the soul itself are <seg
            ana="#manifestus">obvious</seg> to us: For <seg
            ana="#artificialis">productive</seg> <seg
            ana="#operatio">activities</seg> are known to use, but they cannot
            take place without <seg ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg>, and
            <seg ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg> procedes from some sort
            of <seg ana="#potentia">power</seg>, and a <seg
            ana="#potentia">power</seg> flows from the <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg>; and it is the same with other <seg
            ana="#operatio">activities</seg> <supplied>such as those</supplied>
            which procede from the irascible. Thus, by many things which are
            known to us we may arrive at a <seg ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg>
            about the soul. But <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> <seg
            ana="#scire">knowing</seg> is <seg ana="#cognoscere">knowing</seg>
            through causes, and such <seg ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg> about
            the soul proceeds by effects, not by causes, the <name
            ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> therefore, as he presents the
            <seg ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg> about the soul, calls the <seg
            ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg>
            <cit>
              <quote>an account</quote>
              <bibl>Arist. <title ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title> I.1 402a4</bibl>
            </cit>
            . But by extension it can be called a science.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#ad-rationes-contra">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-1mle08" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="1">
            To the first argument it must be said that the minor premise is
            false. And to the <seg ana="#probatio">supporting argument</seg> it
            must be said that something is available to sense perception in two
            ways: either by <unclear>its possession</unclear> or by privation. By
            privation just like shadows and indivisible objects, such as a point
            and a unity. By <unclear>possession</unclear> in two ways: either by
            its own <seg ana="#species">species</seg> or by the <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg> of something else; when by its own <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg>, it is just like when a colour is seen,
            <cit>
              <quote type="paraphrase">
                when by the <seg ana="#species">species</seg> of something else,
                it is just like when the son of Diares is seen.
              </quote>
              <bibl>
                Arist. <title ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title> II.6 418a20--22
              </bibl>
            </cit>
            . <seg ana="#unde">Hence</seg> although the soul is not available to
            sense perception in itself, it is still available to sense
            perception by something else, that is by its effects, and in the
            same way,
            <app>
              <lem>
                although it does not produce phantasms on its own, it produces
                another phantasm, which may lead to <seg
                ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg> about it.
              </lem>
              <note>
                The Latin reads: <quote>licet per se phantasma non faciat, aliud
                [aliquid MS] tamen phantasma facit, quod in eius cognitionem
                ducere potest.</quote> We must understand this to mean
                that the although there cannot be a phantasm of the soul, as it
                is not perceptible, it produces an external activity that may
                yield phantasms by which we can acquire knowledge about the
                soul as origin of those activities. The manuscript reading
                <mentioned>something</mentioned> is thus replaced by
                <mentioned>another</mentioned> to emphasise the externality
                (but not contingency) of the produced activities.
              </note>
            </app>
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-i9rohp" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="2">
            To the next it must be said that <seg ana="#motus">movement</seg> is
            said in two ways: in one way it is the act of an imperfect object,
            just as it is defined by the <name
            ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> in
            <cit>
              <ref>
                the third book of the <title ref="#Arist.Phys">Physics</title>;
              </ref>
              <bibl>
                Arist. <title ref="#Arist.Phys">Phys.</title> III.2 201b31--33
              </bibl>
            </cit>
            , and in another way it is the act of the perfect being, just as
            <seg ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg> and <seg
            ana="#sentire">cognition</seg> are said to be movement: In the first
            way the same thing cannot be moving and moved by itself, but
            accidentally nothing prevents it, just as the sailor moves the ship
            by himself, and in that being moved he moves himself. In the other
            way nothing prevents the same thing from moving itself. But there is
            although a difference: For there is one sort of substance which
            always actively <seg ana="#intelligere_ptc">knows</seg>, and such a
            substance can <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg> by itself, just as
            it is the case with the first cause and the intelligences; but there
            is another sort of substance which does not always actively <seg
            ana="#intelligere_ptc">know</seg>, just as the human soul, and such
            a thing does not <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg> by itself, <seg
            ana="#quia">since</seg> it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg>
            nothing except when it is actualized, and such a substance, <seg
            ana="#cum+subj">since</seg> it potentially <seg
            ana="#intelligere_ptc">knows</seg>, is not actualized except by
            something else, that is by a intelligible <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg>, and <seg ana="#ideo">therefore</seg>
            it can <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg> itself through something
            else. For by the fact that the soul <seg
            ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> and object by a <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg> it can <seg
            ana="#intelligere">know</seg> its own activity, and by the activity
            it can <seg ana="#reflectere">reflect</seg> itself on its own <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg>; <seg ana="#unde">hence</seg> our soul
            in a certain way <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself just as
            the sailor moves the ship.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-52psh5" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="3">
            To the next it must be said that although the eye of the night-raven
            cannot apprehend the light of the sun directly, it can although
            apprehend some brightness indirectly, and if its sight were
            discursive, then it could <seg ana="#cognoscere">know</seg> the
            light of the sun. But now, although our intellect cannot arrive at a
            perfect <seg ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg> about the separate
            substances, some of their effects are still apparent to us by which
            we may be led to a <seg ana="#notitia">knowledge</seg> about them,
            and <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> our intellect is discursive, <seg
            ana="#ideo">therefore</seg> it can arrive at some sort of <seg
            ana="#cognitio">knowledge</seg> of them through their effects. But
            we <seg ana="#cognoscere">know</seg> more about the soul than about
            the separate substances, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> the effects of
            the soul itself, which are apparent to us, are more suited to its
            <seg ana="#virtus">power</seg> than the effects of the separate
            substances, which are apparent to us, are suited to their <seg
            ana="#virtues">power</seg>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-h6ks8n" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="4">
            To the next it must be said that our <seg
            ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg> does not take place without
            phantasms, continuously and temporally, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg>
            it does not take place without phantasms. But it does not <seg
            ana="#oportere">require</seg> that all <seg
            ana="#intelligere">intellection</seg> is continous and temporal.
          </p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
