<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Quaestiones in libros De anima</title>
        <author>Johannes Dinsdale</author>
        <editor>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</editor>
        <editor role="translator">Michael Stenskjær Christensen</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1.0-dev">
          <date when="2016-11-13">November 13, 2016</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</publisher>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref
          target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative
          Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="bal">
            Oxford, Balliol College 311, ff. 148r--181v
          </witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
      <schemaRef n="lbp-critical-1.0.0"
                 target="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/1.0/critical.rng">
      </schemaRef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>
          Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the
          LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a critical edition
        </p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="draft">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2016-11-13" status="draft" n="0.1.0">
          <p>First draft of finished edition.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="la" type="translation">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on">
        <pb ed="#B" n="174-v" /><cb ed="#B" n="a"/>
      </div>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="itemdid">
        <head>
          <supplied ana="#meta-text">
            Question 15: Whether the intellect <seg
            ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself by its <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg> or by something else just as it knows
            other things
          </supplied>
        </head>
        <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-h7abaq">
          It is asked whether the intellect <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg>
          itself by its <seg ana="#essentia">essence</seg> or by something else
          just as it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> other things.
        </p>
        <div ana="#rationes-principales-contra">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-kr6i2n" type="rationes-principales">
            It seems that it <supplied>knows itself</supplied> by its <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-ttgne1" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="1">
            Because things that are <seg ana="#intelligere">known</seg> by
            the intellect are <seg ana="#intelligere">known</seg> by something
            other than their <seg ana="#essentia">essence</seg>, such as their
            <seg ana="#species">species</seg>; but what is intelligible, in so
            far as it is intelligible, is one in <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg>; <seg ana="#ergo">thus</seg> if the
            intellect were intelligible by something else just as other things,
            and <seg ana="#cum+ind">when</seg> the intellect, aside from the
            fact that it is intelligible, <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg>,
            then all other things, aside from the fact that they are
            intelligible, would also <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-z4t4fo" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="2">
            Further, in beings that are separate from matter that which knows
            and that which is known are the same thing; but the intellect is
            separate from matter; <seg ana="#ergo">thus</seg> in the intellect
            the same thing is <seg ana="#intelligere">knowing</seg> and known,
            thus it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself by itself.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-bd4395" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="3">
            Further, intelligence and human intellect meet in the genus of
            intelligible objects; but an intelligence <seg
            ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself by its <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg>; <seg ana="#ergo">thus</seg> the human
            intellect <supplied>does too</supplied>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-ytwlis" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="4">
            Further, the act of <seg ana="#intelligere">knowing</seg> arises
            from the unity of the intelligible and the intellect; but nothing is
            more united with the intellect than it is with itself; <seg
            ana="#ergo">thus</seg> it cannot <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg>
            <supplied>itself</supplied> by anything but itself.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-a5w2gi" ana="#rationes-principales-contra"
             n="5">
            Further, the intellect <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself.
            <seg ana="#ergo">Thus</seg> it is either by its own <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg>, by a <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg>, or by its activity; but it is neither
            by a <seg ana="#species">species</seg> nor by its own activity; <seg
            ana="#ergo">thus</seg> it must be by its own <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg>. Proof of the assumption: Neither by
            <seg ana="#species">species</seg>, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> an
            intelligible object is abstracted from phantasms, and the intellect
            does not produce phantasms; nor by its activity, <seg
            ana="#quia">since</seg> if it <seg ana="#intelligere">knew</seg> its
            activity, it would <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg> itself by some
            other activity. <seg ana="#ergo">Thus</seg> that activity either
            <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> or does not know. If it does not
            know, the same would hold for the first, if it does know, <seg
            ana="#ergo">thus</seg> it will be by another activity, and in this
            way it will be possible to proceed in infinity. Further, a
            particular sense does not sense its activity, <seg
            ana="#ergo">thus</seg> neither does the intellect <seg
            ana="#intelligere">know</seg> its activity.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#rationes-principales-pro">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-9wb9sg">
            The <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says the opposite in
            the third book of <title ref="#Arist.DA">De anima</title>. For he
            says that
            <cit>
              <quote>
                the intellect <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself
                just like other things
              </quote>
              <bibl ana="arist.DA.3.4.430a2">
                Arist. <title ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title>, III.4 430a2
              </bibl>
            </cit>
            ; but it does not <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg> other things by
            their <seg ana="#essentia">essences</seg> but by their <seg
            ana="#species">species</seg>; <seg ana="#ergo">thus</seg>
            <supplied>the intellect</supplied> <seg
            ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself in the same way.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#determinatio">
          <div ana="#determinatio" n="1">
            <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-0ic4br">
              It must be said that the intellect does not <seg
              ana="#intelligere">know</seg> itself by its <seg
              ana="#essentia">essence</seg>, and the reason for that is: Nothing
              is know except in accordance with its actuality, hence nothing is
              true as something that is available to the cognition of the
              intellect, except in accordance with its actuality, as the <name
              ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says in the ninth book of the
              <title ref="#Arist.Metaph">Metaphysics</title>.
              <cit>
                <quote type="paraphrase">
                  Indeed, just as sight does not see nor <seg
                  ana="#cognoscere">know</seg> something potentially coloured
                  but something actually coloured, in the same way does the
                  intellect not know
                </quote>
                <bibl>Arist. <title ref="#Arist.Metaph">Metaph.</title>, IX.9
                1051a29--31, cf. <title ref="#Auct.Arist">Auct. Arist.</title>
                (ed. Hamesse), 6.234.</bibl>
              </cit>
              , and therefore, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> matter is being in
              potentiality, it does not known except through the form by which
              it is actualized. As a proof of this it must taken into
              consideration that there is an intellect which is pure and perfect
              actuality, such as the intellect of God, and it <seg
              ana="#cognoscere">knows</seg> itself such that it <seg
              ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> by its <seg
              ana="#essentia">essence</seg> and all other things by itself;
              there is another intellect which is in actuality but is not
              perfect act, such as the intellect of an intelligence, <seg
              ana="#quia">since</seg> it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg>
              itself by its <seg ana="#essentia">essence</seg>, but it does not
              know other things by itself but by their similitudes. But the
              human intellect is not in actuality by itself, and is therefore
              called possible, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> by itself it is in
              potentiality, and does therefore not have the cause for its being
              known from itself. But it does have the cause for its knowing from
              itself; indeed just as <name ref="#Plato">Plato</name> says that
              <cit>
                <quote type="paraphrase">
                  intelligibile objects are separate and that our intellect is
                  intelligible by its participation in those intelligible objects
                </quote>
              </cit>
              , it is possible for the <name
              ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name>, when he says that
              <cit>
                <quote type="paraphrase">
                  <seg ana="#species">species</seg> are abstracted from
                  intelligible phantasms
                </quote>
                <note>
                  <title ref="#Arist.DA">De anima</title> III.8 432a8-9 cf.
                  <name ref="#Aquinas">Aquinas</name>, <title
                  ref="#Aquin.SentDA">Sent. de anima</title> lib. 3, cap. 7, p.
                  236, ll. 72--89. See also <title
                  ref="#Aquin.SentDA">ibid.</title> lib. 3, cap. 4, p. 218, ll.
                  8--23 and p. 220, ll. 101--121.
                </note>
              </cit>
              , to say that our intellect is intelligible according to its
              participation in those <seg ana="#species">species</seg>, and he
              does this in the following way: Since our intellect <seg
              ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> an object by its <seg
              ana="#species">species</seg>, it is able to revert on its own
              activity, and from the activity it can proceed to its power, and
              from the power to the <seg ana="#essentia">essence</seg>, and thus
              by being actualized by another species it can <seg
              ana="#intelligere">know</seg> its own activity, and by the
              activity <supplied>it can know</supplied> itself. Hence that which
              is first known by a part of the intellect is its actuality, which
              is its final perfection. <seg ana="#quia">Since</seg> <seg
              ana="#intelligere">knowing</seg> is not an activity that has an
              effect outside itself, such as cooling and building, but rather
              remains in the operating subject, therefore <seg
              ana="#intelligere">knowing</seg> is not a perfection of some
              external thing like it is the case with building, but is the
              perfection of the intellect itself.
            </p>
          </div>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-g6oie8" ana="#determinatio" n="2">
            But this activity can <unclear>understand</unclear> in two ways. In
            one way in the particular, such as when it perceives that it is
            itself actually <seg ana="#intelligere">knowing</seg>, and in
            another way in the universal, such as when it investigates its own
            particular <unclear>activity</unclear> through its object. And in
            the same way it can <seg ana="#intelligere">know</seg> its own <seg
            ana="#essentia">essence</seg> in two ways: In one way in the
            particular, such as when it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> that
            which it has, such as when <name ref="#Socrates">Socrates</name>
            perceives himself having an intellect by the fact that he <seg
            ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> in actuality, and in another way in
            the universal, such as when it inquires about the nature of the
            intellect through its <unclear>activity</unclear>. And these ways
            differ, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> the presence of the intellect
            that is actualized in an activity suffices for the first <seg
            ana="#cognitio">cognition</seg>, but for the second <seg
            ana="#cognitio">cognition</seg> a subtle and distinguishing
            inquisition is required, and for this reason many are ignorant about
            the nature of the intellect and many are wrong about it.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div ana="#ad-rationes-contra">
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-qo6iip" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="1">
            To the first argument it must be said that the intellect and that
            which is known are the same in actuality, and not intellect and that
            which is known in potentiality. Now, the intelligible species is the
            immediate principle of knowledge. Hence wherever there is a
            intelligible species in actuality, it can know, but whichever
            species that is in the stone or in a material thing outside the
            intellect is only intelligible in potency, and therefore no
            intelligible thing outside our intellect has its immediate principle of
            knowledge in itself, and for that reason cannot know. But a species
            which is in the intellect is intelligible in actuality, and
            therefore, <seg ana="#cum+subj">since</seg> our intellect has its
            immediate principle of knowledge in itself, it can know aside from
            the fact that it is intelligible, and it is not in this way in other things.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-438wxb" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="2">
            To the second argument it must be said that these things are said to
            be separate from matter which are known in actuality. Hence,
            <cit>
              <ref>
                the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says in the third
                book of <title ref="#Arist.DA">De anima</title>
              </ref>
              <quote type="paraphrase">
                exactly in the same way as things are separable from matter so
                it is the case for the intellect
              </quote>
              <bibl>Arist. <title ref="#Arist.DA">De anima</title> III.4 429b21--2</bibl>
            </cit>
            , but that which is known in actuality and the intellect are the
            same, just as that which is perceptible in actuality and the sense.
            For certainly the perceptible in actuality and sense are not the
            same except because the same form belongs to both, <seg
            ana="#quia">since</seg> the <seg ana="#species">species</seg> which
            is caused by something perceptible, as by an agent, is in the
            sense as in a subject, and in the same way in the
            <unclear>proposition</unclear>: That which is known in actuality and
            the intellect are said to be the same, because the species of that
            which is known in actuality is the realizing form which informs the
            intellect, and by this form the intellect knows by traversion over
            itself and not by its essence.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-kimcp2" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="3">
            To the third argument it must be said that the intellect of the
            intelligence is perfect actuality because it always is actualized.
            For in itself is has connate species. But in itself our intellect is
            in potentiality as possible, and the agent intellect itself, insofar
            as it is actualized, is the actualization of the intelligible
            things, and not known before it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg>.
          </p>
          <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-pp01nh" ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="4">
            To the fourth it must be said that the act of knowing is caused by
            the union of the object and the intellect, but although nothing is
            more united with the intellect than it is with itself, it still
            cannot be united with itself as an object, because the object of our
            intellect is the nature of a thing which is outside the soul, and
            that cannot be united with the intellect except by a species.
          </p>
          <div ana="#ad-rationes-contra" n="5">
            <p xml:id="da-49-l3q15-9twekw">
              To the final argument it must be said that it knows itself both by
              a species and by an activity, but not by its own species, which
              the argument proves, but by a species which belongs to something
              else. Similarly it <seg ana="#intelligere">knows</seg> itself by
              its own activity, and it knows that activity by still another
              activity. Therefore it must be understood that there is an
              intellect which is its own <seg ana="#intelligere">knowing</seg>,
              and therefore it knows its own essence and own knowing by a
              unitary activity, <seg ana="#quia">since</seg> they are the same,
              as the intellect of God. And there is another intellect which is
              not its own knowing, but by its essence it is object of its own
              knowing, such as the intellect of an intelligence, and although
              its knowing and its essence differ, it still knows its own essence
              and own knowing by a unitary act, since knowing is the perfection
              of its essence, and a thing and its perfection are known by a
              unitary act. But the human intellect is neither its own knowing
              nor is its essence object of its own knowing, and therefore it
              cannot know the object and its own knowing by a unitary act,
              because its knowing is not the perfection of its object. For
              knowing the stone is not the perfection of the stone, but it is
              the perfection of the intellect, and therefore it is not possible
              to know the stone and the knowing itself by a unitary act. Hence
              by this it must be said to the argument that it knows its own
              activity and its object by a different activity, and it knows that
              activity in actuality, and thus infinitely, and it is not
              inconvenient to proceed infinitely in activities of the intellect
              and reason.
            </p>
            <p xml:id="da-49-l1q1-acort9">
              To the second proof it must be said that a sense senses by an
              alteration of a corporeal organ, and nothing corporeal alters
              itself, and therefore the sense is not altered except by something
              external. But the intellect is not altered by the alteration of
              the corporeal organ, but spiritually, and something spiritual can
              easily turn itself on itself, and therefore Plato said that the
              first mover moves itself, since the first mover could be soul and
              its activities, just as to love and cherish, and in this way it
              could be its movement.
            </p>
          </div>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
