<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/out/critical.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Quaestiones in libros De anima</title>
        <author>Johannes Dinsdale</author>
        <editor>Michael Stenskjær Christensen</editor>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition n="0.1.1-dev">
          <date when="2017-05-26"/>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>
          <ref target="http://representationandreality.gu.se">
            Representation and Reality: Historical and Contemporary Perspectives
            on the Aristotelian Tradition
          </ref>
        </authority>
        <availability status="free">
          <p>Published under a <ref target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs 3.0 License</ref></p>
        </availability>
        <date when="2017-04-12">April 12, 2017</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <listWit>
          <witness xml:id="O" n="oriel33">Oxford, Oriel College Library 33, ff. 164r-182v</witness>
          <witness xml:id="B" n="bal">Oxford, Balliol College 311, ff. 148r--181v</witness>
        </listWit>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <schemaRef
          n="lbp-diplomatic-1.0.0"
          url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/lombardpress/lombardpress-schema/master/src/diplomatic.rng">
      </schemaRef>
      <editorialDecl>
        <p>Encoding of this text has followed the recommendations of the LombardPress 1.0.0 guidelines for a diplomatic edition</p>
        <p>The transcription has been normalized to classical orthography.</p>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc status="published">
      <listChange>
        <change when="2017-04-12" status="draft" n="2017.04">
          <p>Created file for the first time.</p>
        </change>
        <change when="2017-05-26" status="out-for-review" n="0.1.0">
          <p>The text has been sent for review.</p>
        </change>
        <change when="2017-05-26" status="out-for-review" n="0.1.1-dev">
          <p>Encoding corrections.</p>
        </change>
        <change when="2017-07-24" status="out-for-review" n="0.1.2">
          <p>Make review changes.</p>
        </change>
        <change when="2017-08-14" status="published" n="1.0.0">
          <p>Published on http://cimagl.saxo.ku.dk/download/86/86christensen79-131.pdf.</p>
        </change>
      </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en" type="translation">
    <front>
      <div xml:id="starts-on"/>
    </front>
    <body>
      <div xml:id="translation-da-49-l1prooemium">
        <head>Prologue</head>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-l1prooemium-gq0450">
          <cit>
            <quote type="lemma">Of good and honourable things et cetera</quote>
            <bibl>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
              ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title> I.1 402a1.
            </bibl>
          </cit>
          . In the second book of <title ref="Arist.Ph">Physics</title>, as he intends to
          investigate and present the boundaries and limits of the study of
          physics and of the natural philosopher, the
          <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says
          <cit>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              to which extent the natural philosopher ought to investigate the
              species and essence
            </quote>
            <bibl><name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
            ref="#Arist.Ph">Ph.</title> II.2 194b10--11.</bibl>
          </cit>
          , <abbr>viz.</abbr> what the limits are of the study of physics or of
          the natural philosopher concerning species,
          <abbr>i.e.</abbr> forms, which are the essences, <abbr>i.e.</abbr>
          which are relevant to the definition of the essence. He answers
          <cit>
            <ref>
              in the same passage
            </ref>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              that just as the doctor investigates nerves and the smith metal,
              so the natural philosopher investigates the form or species and
              essence,
            </quote>
            <bibl><name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title>Ph.</title> II.2 194b11--12.</bibl>
          </cit>
          . For not just any consideration of nerves pertains to the doctor, nor
          does whatever thing that can be known about metal pertain to the
          smith, and similarly not every consideration of forms pertains to the
          natural philosopher. We must therefore consider how these artificers
          investigate the mentioned subjects.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-1zdal1">
          Let us consider what the different subject matters of the doctor, the
          smith and the natural philosopher are. A doctor primarily seeks to
          produce good health in them, so when he investigates nerves, it aims
          at the production of good health; therefore every investigation of
          nerves pertains to the doctor, insofar as it strives for good health,
          but if there is some other consideration that goes beyond this, it
          supersedes the doctor's investigation. Similarly, as the smith focuses
          on matter of artificial instruments, any investigation of metal, qua
          the matter of artificial instruments, pertains to the smith, but if
          there is some consideration that goes beyond this, it stays beyond his
          purveiw. From this it is apparent of what sort of object the natural
          philosopher's knowledge is and to which limit it extends. For whatever
          is considered by a natural philosopher is characterized by movement
          and change,
          <cit>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              for things which move but are not moved do not fall within the
              natural philosopher's purview
            </quote>
            <ref>
              according to the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> in
              <title ref="#Arist.Ph">Physics</title> II
            </ref>
            <bibl>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
              ref="#Arist.Ph">Ph.</title> II.7 198a26--30.
            </bibl>
          </cit>
          . Hence entirely immaterial forms which are not linked to matter which
          is subject to motion and change, escape the purview of the
          physicist or natural philosopher. But forms which in one way are
          immaterial and in another way are the perfection of matter do fall
          within the purview of the natural philosopher or physicist, and
          that is the limit to which the physical study extends. But the
          human soul is that sort of form, and hence it is the limit and end of
          physical study.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-jon4qo">
          And from this we can establish that there are three types of forms.
          For some are entirely immaterial, both with respect to their
          disposition and substance, and such are the intelligences, which exist
          without any sensible or intelligible matter
          <cit>
            <ref>
              according to the <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> in
              <title ref="#Arist.Metaph">Metaphysics</title> VIII
            </ref>
            <bibl>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
              ref="#Arist.Metaph">Metaph.</title> VIII.5 1044b27--29(?).
            </bibl>
          </cit>
          . Some are entirely material, both with respect to their substance and
          disposition, since their substances and dispositions are drawn from
          matter, and the forms of the things here below are of this sort. But
          some are forms of a medial character which are immaterial with respect
          to their substance and material with respect to their dispositions,
          and the human souls are of this sort. Hence the first forms are beyond
          the purview of the natural philosopher, but the physical study begins
          with the second forms and terminates with the third, for the study of
          the natural philosopher begins with the lower forms and ends with
          the human soul.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-arr3uu">
          From this it is furthermore clear which place this book holds among
          the books on natural philosophy, as the physical and the metaphysical
          mode of investigation in some way are opposed each other. For the
          natural philosopher's mode of investigation has an upper limit but not
          a lower one, for it has a limit with regard to the level of
          abstraction, which is the upper limit, since some things are so
          abstract that they are beyond physical study, and some are so abstract
          that physical study does not go beyond them. But with regard to the
          level of concreteness, which is the lower level, the natural
          philosopher does not have a limit, for there is no form so concreted
          with matter it falls outside the natural philosopher's subject matter.
          Thus the more concreted a form is with matter, the more it falls
          within his subject matter, and this must be understood in such a way
          that the abstraction from singular items is presupposed, for if we
          look to things individual and numerically singular, they fall outside
          of the natural philosopher's subject matter. But the contrary holds
          for the metaphysician's mode of investigation, since it has a lower
          limit but not an upper one, because some forms are so concrete with
          respect to matter that the consideration of them does not pertain to
          the metaphysician, but there is no form so abstract that it exceeds
          the metaphysician's consideration, for metaphysics is concerned with
          the highest causes. Hence the more an investigation is concerned with
          abstract things, the more metaphysical it is. This must be understood
          with reference to a study based on human inquiry, for if there is
          some abstract study which is acquired through inspiration, it exceeds
          the metaphysician's subject matter, but that sort of consideration is
          not within the purview of the present investigation.
        </p>
        <p xml:id="translation-da-49-prooemium-gurt68">
          Hence let us understand what has been said in the following way, that
          when there are three essential parts of philosophy (namely natural
          philosophy, mathematics, and divine science) among the arts or
          sciences found through human inquiry, the metaphysician does not
          recognize any higher science, but in terms of the level of abstraction
          natural philosophy does not recognize any lower practitioner within
          the essential parts of philosophy, although there is a higher one, but
          the mathematician recognizes both a higher practice, since there is a
          more abstract one, and a lower, since there is one more concrete.
          Hence, as it has been said, the natural philosopher's subject matter
          takes its beginning with the lower forms and ends with the human soul,
          and from this it is clear that <title ref="#Arist.DA">On the
          soul</title> holds the sixth place within the books on natural
          philosophy, for <title ref="#Arist.Ph">Physics</title> holds the first
          place, <title ref="#Arist.Cael">On the heavens and earth</title> the
          second, <title ref="#Arist.GC">On generation and corruption</title>
          the third, <title ref="#Arist.Met">Meteorology</title> the fourth,
          <title ref="#Ps-Arist.Min">On minerals</title> the fifth, and <title
          ref="#Arist.DA">On the soul</title> the sixth. It is therefore the
          first in order of dignity, although it is the last or sixth in the
          order of teaching, and hence the
          <cit>
            <ref>
              <name ref="#Aristotle">Philosopher</name> says, with a view to its
              dignity,
            </ref>
            <quote type="paraphrase">
              that the description of the soul should be ranked among the first
              sciences.
            </quote>
            <bibl><name ref="#Aristotle">Arist.</name> <title
            ref="#Arist.DA">DA</title> I.1 402a1--7.</bibl>
          </cit>
        </p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
